Running preflight checks...
Running preflight checks... PASSED
Repairing missing prerequisites...
COO: build artifacts ...
COO: build artifacts OK
Recording install state...
Recording install state... PASSED
Running preflight checks...
Running preflight checks... PASSED
ADF preflight OK

--- Launching COO ---
  mode: tsx-direct
  cwd:  /c/ADF/.codex/implement-plan/worktrees/phase1/coo-live-executive-status-wiring/COO
  cmd:  /c/ADF/.codex/implement-plan/worktrees/phase1/coo-live-executive-status-wiring/COO/node_modules/.bin/tsx.cmd controller/cli.ts --scope assafyavnai/adf --enable-onion --status --scope-path assafyavnai/adf/phase1


# COO Executive Status

**Bottom line**

22 features shipped in the recent window. Nothing is actively executing right now. 2 systemic issues need your decision before we move forward.

---

**Delivery health**

- 22 features landed in the recent window.
- 16 of 22 have full review-cycle evidence; 2 more are acceptable legacy items.
- 19 of 22 have proved pre-merge approval on record.
- 18 of 22 landed features are missing durable KPI cost totals; the work shipped, but the receipts did not.

---

**Issues that need a decision**

1. COO dashboard blind spot (HIGH - immediate)

Recent work is not consistently making it into the COO reporting surface, so this brief can miss live context.
Evidence: The active implement-plan worktree for Coo Live Executive Status Wiring is present, but the final COO brief still does not visibly carry it.
Fix: Wire the missing active slice into the COO surface before relying on this update for prioritization.

---

2. Cost auditability gap (HIGH - immediate - affects 18 items)

Our closeout route is dropping delivery cost totals after work ships, so we proved the work landed but cannot fully audit what it cost.
Evidence: 18 of 22 recent landings are missing durable KPI totals.
Fix: patch the implement-plan closeout projection so post-rollout landings persist KPI token totals into durable truth, then backfill the affected landed slices. Handoff is prepared and can move to implement-plan immediately if approved

---

**Parked / waiting**

- The implement-plan closeout route is dropping post-rollout KPI token totals from durable closeout truth. - Without durable token totals on post-rollout landings, the COO cannot fully audit delivery cost or compare company efficiency across recent work.
- /status command in the COO CLI - Review the finalized requirement for technical admission.
- This item is being carried with fallback evidence because Thread Onion is missing. - Awaiting follow-up.
- This item is being carried with fallback evidence because CTO Admission is missing. - Awaiting follow-up.

---

**Recommendation**

Fix COO dashboard blind spot first, then cost auditability gap. It is the highest-leverage route risk in the current brief.

Where would you like to focus?

1. **COO dashboard blind spot** (Recommended) - Wire the missing active slice into the COO surface before relying on this update for prioritization.
2. **Cost auditability gap** - patch the implement-plan closeout projection so post-rollout landings persist KPI token totals into durable truth, then backfill the affected landed slices. Handoff is prepared and can move to implement-plan immediately if approved
3. **Show detailed breakdown** - Review the detailed breakdown before deciding.
4. **Other** - type what you need

